<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>The path of coding enlightment</title>
  <id>http://shiroyasha.io/</id>
  <link href="http://shiroyasha.io/"/>
  <link href="http://shiroyasha.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2025-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Everything Around You Was Someone's Passion Project</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/everything-around-you-was-someones-passion-project.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/everything-around-you-was-someones-passion-project.html</id>
    <published>2025-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-02-16T14:50:40+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look around. Really look. That keyboard you’re typing on, the chair you’re
sitting in, the room you’re in, the building you’re in, the bakery at the end
of your street that sells that amazing bread, your freedom to walk down the
street without fear...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look around. Really look. That keyboard you&amp;rsquo;re typing on, the chair you&amp;rsquo;re
sitting in, the room you&amp;rsquo;re in, the building you&amp;rsquo;re in, the bakery at the end
of your street that sells that amazing bread, your freedom to walk down the
street without fear of being arrested, the ability to read and write, the
ability to communicate with people on the other side of the planet. I can go on
forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re surrounded by other people&amp;rsquo;s devotion and hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not hyporbole. It&amp;rsquo;s fact. Everything you see around you was someone&amp;rsquo;s
passion project. Before the mass production, before the focus groups, before
the value engineering. There was just someone who coudn&amp;rsquo;t let go of an idea.
Someone who looked at the impossible problem and said &amp;ldquo;I can solve this&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s bothering me in Europe right now: We&amp;rsquo;ve become excellent at
pointing out problems. Master critiques. Professional complainers about
everything from government inefficiency to technological stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We write lengthy threads about what&amp;rsquo;s wrong. &lt;br /&gt;
We share detailed analyses of system failures.  &lt;br /&gt;
We craft elegant critiques of institutional problems. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then we wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait for someone else to fix it. Wait for solutions to come from above. Wait
for the system to somehow reform itself. This isn&amp;rsquo;t analysis. It&amp;rsquo;s learned
helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve been conditioned by decades of imperial power structures to think that
change comes from outside. That our role is to merely identify problems, 
complain a lot, and then wait for someone else to fix them. Actual 
implementation is someone else&amp;rsquo;s job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything around us was built by people ignored such compaints. They didn&amp;rsquo;t 
write treatises about why things are broken. They didn&amp;rsquo;t wait for perfect 
conditions. They didn&amp;rsquo;t expect someone else to solve their problems. We didn&amp;rsquo;t
wait for America to innovate for us. We didn&amp;rsquo;t wait for China to manufacture
for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first democracy wasn&amp;rsquo;t built by people waiting for kings to give up power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last three months, my country is the best example of how to break this
cycle. We&amp;rsquo;ve been through a lot in the last couple of decades. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our 
institutions fail us. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our leaders betray us and divide us. We&amp;rsquo;ve 
seen our systems collapse. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our people suffer. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen corruption,
incompetence, and greed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we&amp;rsquo;ve also seen something else. In the last three months, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen students
raise their voices. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen teachers, doctors, and engineers join them. We&amp;rsquo;ve
seen people from all walks of life come together to change things. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen
people who were told to wait for oposition parties to fix things, take matters
into their own hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what Europe needs to learn from this: The right time to start building
was 30 years ago. We fucked it up. The second best time is now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everything Around You Was Someone's Passion Project</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/everything-around-you-was-someone-s-passion-project.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/everything-around-you-was-someone-s-passion-project.html</id>
    <published>2025-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-02-16T13:40:49+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html"></summary>
    <content type="html"></content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Work can wait, your wedding can't</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/work-can-wait-your-weddig-cant.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/work-can-wait-your-weddig-cant.html</id>
    <published>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-10-08T18:45:59+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I saw something insane on LinkedIn today. A founder bragging about his
co-founder about submitting a pull-request during his own wedding. Let that
sink in for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started working in the industry, I thought I knew what hard work was.
Working...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I saw something insane on LinkedIn today. A founder bragging about his
co-founder about submitting a pull-request during his own wedding. Let that
sink in for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started working in the industry, I thought I knew what hard work was.
Working until my eyes bled out and my fingers were numb. I was wrong. True
hard work isn&amp;rsquo;t about grinding until you drop. It&amp;rsquo;s about passion, focus,
and knowing when to step back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the reality: You can always find another reason to keep working. Just
one more line of code, one more bug to fix. But you can&amp;rsquo;t get back the moments
you miss. You&amp;rsquo;re wedding day is once in a lifetime. No product launch, no
matter how groundbraking will ever compare to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn&amp;rsquo;t just about weddings. It is about the idea that work should consume
every aspect of your life. That you are not commintted unless you are always on.
Always grinding for that carrot that you put infront of yourself. Bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real work - good work - doesn&amp;rsquo;t come from a place of exhaustion. It happens in
focused burst. It happens when you are well-rested, well-fed, and well-loved. The
bug that you are grinding for hours, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably get the right idea when you
are out on walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are things that are actually impressive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shipping great products consistently&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a business that respects people&amp;rsquo;s time and energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enjoying your wedding day with your friends and family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to stop glorifying overwork. If your business can&amp;rsquo;t survive you taking day
off for your wedding, then you don&amp;rsquo;t have a business, you have a ticking time bomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, our legacy won&amp;rsquo;t be the 2k lines of code we wrote on our wedding day.
It will be the relationships we built, the inspiration we gave, and the innovation
we brought to the world. That is the kind of success worth pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work can wait. Your wedding can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Social Parasites</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/social-parasites.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/social-parasites.html</id>
    <published>2024-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-10-06T18:32:13+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve recently witnessed a perfect example of this parasitic behavior. A
startup, freshly minted by a once-respected incubator, had the audacity to fork
an open-source project and claim it as their own. They didn’t innovate. They
didn’t improve. They...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve recently witnessed a perfect example of this parasitic behavior. A
startup, freshly minted by a once-respected incubator, had the audacity to fork
an open-source project and claim it as their own. They didn&amp;rsquo;t innovate. They
didn&amp;rsquo;t improve. They simply took.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear: I&amp;rsquo;m not talking about healthy competition or even inspiration
drawn from existing ideas. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about those who shamelessly and completely
take the hard work of others, wrapping it in a shiny new package and calling it
their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what happened: This startup PairAI basically took an open-source project 
called Continue, forked it, and are now passing it off as their own groundbreaking
innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the kick-you-in-the-balls: YC&amp;rsquo;s CEO, Garry Tan, defended this copycat
behavior on Twitter. Talk about missing the forest for the trees. Sure, it might
be legal, but that&amp;rsquo;s not the point. The point is that YC is funding startups 
with zero innovation and apparently zero due diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being inspired by other projects is one thing. Heck, it&amp;rsquo;s how most of us get
started. I&amp;rsquo;m even fine with copying. But taking someone else&amp;rsquo;s work, changing a 
few lines of code, and calling it your own, and then apply to YC and get funded? 
That&amp;rsquo;s a whole different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some might argue that open-source licenses permit such actions. But let me
ask you this: Since when did we start confusing what&amp;rsquo;s legally permissible with
what&amp;rsquo;s ethically right? Since when did &amp;ldquo;not illegal&amp;rdquo; become the bar we&amp;rsquo;re aiming 
for in the tech industry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What message does this send to open-source projects? To the builder and the
maintainers who pour their hearts and souls into open-source projects? It tells
them that their work is up for grabs, ready to be exploited by the first
opportunist who comes along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the thing: Open-source isn&amp;rsquo;t just about the license. It&amp;rsquo;s about the
community. It&amp;rsquo;s about giving back, not just taking. When we use open-source
tools at Operately (and we use them a lot), we always look for ways to contribute
back. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s code, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s documentation, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s just
reporting bugs. But we contribute. Because that&amp;rsquo;s how healthy ecosystems work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can we do about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, if you&amp;rsquo;re an open-source maintainer or contributor, don&amp;rsquo;t let this
discourage you. Keep building, keep sharing. The actions of a few bad actors
don&amp;rsquo;t negate the immense value and importance of what you do. Open-source is
still one of the most powerfull fonces for good, not only in tech, but for the
whole world and society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, to the folks at YC: It&amp;rsquo;s time to step on the brakes. Remember what made
you special in the first place. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t the number of startups you funded. 
It was the quality. The innovation. The community. You are letting it slip
away. For what? A quick flip? A few more unicorns? Is that really worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a successful project is hard. Building a successful company is even
harder. Really hard. There are no shortcurts. And if there were, they certainly 
wouldn&amp;rsquo;t involve ripping off the hard work of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s call this behavior what it is: parasitic. And let&amp;rsquo;s make sure it has no
place in our industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Igor&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Manage Your Time or Someone Else Will Do It for You</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/manage-your-time-or-someone-else-will-do-it-for-you.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/manage-your-time-or-someone-else-will-do-it-for-you.html</id>
    <published>2024-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-10-06T18:32:12+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the moment we’re born, our time isn’t really our own. Parents, schools,
and later, employers all have a say in how our days unfold. As kids, we’re on
someone else’s schedule. Education systems beat it into us, training us to
march to the drum...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the moment we’re born, our time isn’t really our own. Parents, schools,
and later, employers all have a say in how our days unfold. As kids, we’re on
someone else’s schedule. Education systems beat it into us, training us to
march to the drum of a clock that someone else controls. By the time we enter
the workforce, we’re well-prepared to hand over the reins of our time to
another authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people never break free from this pattern. They move from the structure of
school into the rigid framework of corporate life, where time is often wasted
on pointless tasks. Think about the endless meetings you’ve sat
through—meetings that could have been an email, a quick chat, or even avoided
entirely. It’s astonishing how much time we collectively waste on rituals that
serve no real purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The office itself is a masterclass in time-wasting. Long commutes eat away at
your day. Two hours stuck in traffic might not seem like much, but add that up
over a week, a month, a year. Suddenly, you’ve lost hundreds of hours that
could have been spent on something meaningful. That’s time you could’ve used to
learn a new skill, start a side project, or just have some damn fun. Adventures
don’t just happen—they’re made, and you need time to make them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complete work-life separation isn’t optimal either. When you rigidly divide
work from the rest of your life, you end up competing for time and space with
everyone else. The classic example is the gym at 5 p.m. It’s packed, loud, and
stressful. Go at noon, though, and it’s a different world. You have space, you
have time, and you have freedom. Why not work when you’re most productive, and
live when it’s most enjoyable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you measure your team’s output by the hours they spend in a chair, you’re
doing it wrong. It’s naive and lazy management. Forcing people to be present
for a fixed number of hours is a waste, plain and simple. It’s not about the
time spent; it’s about what gets done. When you value chair time over actual
work, you’re collectively making everyone’s life worse. You’re stealing time
from them—their most valuable asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is, if you don’t take control of your time, someone else will. And
they’ll do it in a way that benefits them, not you. Don’t let that happen. Take
the reins, cut out the waste, and reclaim your time. It’s the only way to live
a life that’s truly yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Igor&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Steps We Took to Automate License Compatibility Verification</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/steps-we-took-to-automate-license-compatibility-verification.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/steps-we-took-to-automate-license-compatibility-verification.html</id>
    <published>2024-04-14T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-10-06T17:48:38+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are actively developing Operately, an open-source software licensed under
Apache 2.0. As such, we need to carefully consider whether our dependencies’
licenses are compatible with ours. Starting to build features based on
functionality from a non...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are actively developing Operately, an open-source software licensed under
Apache 2.0. As such, we need to carefully consider whether our dependencies&amp;rsquo;
licenses are compatible with ours. Starting to build features based on
functionality from a non-compatible license, only to realize this too late,
could lead to wasted time and energy in rewriting those features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we are a small team, my attention is intensely focused on building and
refining the core features of Operately. Whenever possible, I take
opportunities to automate tasks that can save significant time in the coming
months. One question arises: can license compatibility checks be automated to a
reasonable degree within a day&amp;rsquo;s work, with a return on the time invested over
the next few months? I implemented such a system a few months ago at Operately.
The return on investment has been decidedly positive, and on several occasions,
it has prevented me from proceeding with features based on an incompatible AGPL
license—a scenario that could have cost me weeks or even a full month of work
if not caught early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My requirements for a license compatibility checking system are as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Integration into the CI Build &amp;amp; Test Phase&lt;/strong&gt;: The system should be
integrated into every continuous integration (CI) run. Whenever someone
pushes code or opens a pull request, the system must provide a clear YES/NO
answer regarding license compatibility. I prefer this real-time check over
asynchronous systems that only notify of issues after code submission.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Comprehensive Dependency Testing&lt;/strong&gt;: The solution must be capable of
testing not only direct dependencies but also their nested dependencies
recursively. It is crucial that it supports Elixir libraries and NPM packages,
given that Operately is developed with a combination of Elixir and React. While
Docker build compatibility would be beneficial, it is not essential.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Open-Source&lt;/strong&gt;: The solution should be open-source. We are committed to
supporting and utilizing open-source solutions, aligning with our principles
and contributing back to the community.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://github.com/pivotal/LicenseFinder"&gt;Pivotal’s License Finder&lt;/a&gt; is an 
excellent solution that meets most of our needs. It is a Ruby-based CLI tool 
that can be installed in our repository and integrated into our continuous 
integration build process. It is compatible with Elixir Mix and NPM, which are
essential for Operately, given our use of Elixir and React. Additionally, it 
supports many other programming languages and build systems, offering flexibility
should we decide to incorporate other technologies into Operately in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial setup of the License Finder can be complex as it involves listing
all the dependencies in your projects and requiring approval for each
discovered license. Here’s the strategy I recommend:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Approve MIT and BSD Licenses&lt;/strong&gt;: These licenses are well-established,
clearly written, and have judicial precedence confirming their compatibility
with the Apache 2.0 license. Approving these is straightforward.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assess Other Open Source Licenses&lt;/strong&gt;: Navigating other open-source licenses
can be more challenging. &lt;a href="https://opensource.org/license"&gt;OpenSource.org&lt;/a&gt; lists 
at least 10 pages of recognized open-source licenses. Some, like GPL3 and AGPL, 
are not compatible with Apache 2.0 and are considered restrictive or even
parasitic. Others, such as Unlicense or WTFPL, lack clear legal status and
are potentially problematic. Since I&amp;rsquo;m not a lawyer, we have decided not to use
such licenses.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Handle Unknown Licenses&lt;/strong&gt;: License Finder sometimes cannot identify a
license for a dependency, like with TipTap used for rich text editing. In
these cases, License Finder allows for the manual approval of packages. It
requires you to specify your identity, the basis of your authorization, and
the reason for approving the use of the license.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deal with License-Less Dependencies&lt;/strong&gt;: Many public repositories on GitHub
are intended to be open-source but lack a clear license, making their use
legally risky. I recommend removing these dependencies or contacting the
contributors to obtain permission to use their software.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Automate the Process&lt;/strong&gt;: Once you have approved all licenses, you can
automate the process by running License Finder in CI. It will check all
dependencies and provide a report on the licenses used. If a new dependency
is added, License Finder will notify you of the new license, allowing you to
approve or reject it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the setup and initial license triage are completed, this system requires
almost no maintenance. It will continuously check every new dependency and every
update to your existing dependencies in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A note of warning:&lt;/strong&gt; While this system is great at detecting most license
incompatibilities, it is not infallible. I recommend a periodic manual reviews 
of all your dependencies, particularly for infrastructure software that this 
solution does not cover.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By investing a day in setting up the License Finder, I have saved myself weeks
of potential rework and legal headaches. I highly recommend this system to
anyone working on open-source projects, especially those with a small team and
limited resources. It is a small investment that can prevent significant
headaches down the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Investing time and energy into automation can yield long-term benefits, but there
is a risk of automating too much too early. For instance, for an early startup
like Operately, it makes sense to automate processes that can provide positive
outcomes within the upcoming quarter and can be completed in under a day.
However, it would be unwise to spend several weeks on automation efforts that do
not promise returns in the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, if you want to look at the specifics of how we implemented this check,
start from here: &lt;a href="https://github.com/operately/operately/blob/main/Makefile#L216"&gt;Operately Makefile&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
