<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>The path of coding enlightment</title>
  <id>http://shiroyasha.io/</id>
  <link href="http://shiroyasha.io/"/>
  <link href="http://shiroyasha.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2025-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Riding the waves of history</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/riding-the-waves-of-history.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/riding-the-waves-of-history.html</id>
    <published>2025-03-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-09-02T13:30:31+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“It’s hard to predict the future,” I texted my friend last week. 
We’d been messaging back and forth about AI, sharing links about 
ChatGPT’s latest image generation capabilities, and debating 
whether programming as we know it is dead. The conversation...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s hard to predict the future,&amp;rdquo; I texted my friend last week. 
We&amp;rsquo;d been messaging back and forth about AI, sharing links about 
ChatGPT&amp;rsquo;s latest image generation capabilities, and debating 
whether programming as we know it is dead. The conversation had 
that familiar mix of excitement, dread, and philosophical hot-takes
that seems to follow most discussions of artificial intelligence 
these days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After sharing some thoughts about how mid-level jobs might be 
affected, I found myself typing: &amp;ldquo;We ride on the waves of history&amp;rdquo;.
It wasn&amp;rsquo;t resignation of the future, but a recognition that some 
forces are bigger than our ability to control them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I&amp;rsquo;ve been wrestling with for months is this: In a world where 
technological change is happening at a pace that makes any five-year
plans seem like a pile of crap, my instinct is to crave certainty.
To look for predictions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend and I had just spent a couple of hours sharing tweets about 
AI-generated ghibli images and debating whether developers and designers
are screwed. We swapped articles with doomsday predictions, then links 
to optimistic counterpoints, searching for some answer that 
would make sense of it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if that&amp;rsquo;s the wrong approach entirely?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve come to believe that our relationship with uncertainty itself may 
be the most important skill to develop in this moment of history. Not 
predictions about AGI timelines or which jobs will be automated or 
if we&amp;rsquo;re months away from digital overlords, but rather, how we position
ourselves mentally when the only certainty is rapid change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning how to surf instead of building ever-higher damns to protect us
from the incoming cunami. How we relate to uncertainty determines everything
downstream: what we build, how we invest our time, what skills we develop, 
and perhaps most importantly, whether we face the future with creative 
optimism or defensive pessimism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Optimists push the world forward,&amp;rdquo; I wrote to him toward the end of our 
conversation. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s talk about riding waves instead of being crushed by them. About 
what it means to live in &lt;em&gt;interesting times&lt;/em&gt; when the only certainty 
is change itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Riding the waves&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t about blind optimism, it is about recognizing that adaptability 
beats prediction every time. The most valuable skill isn&amp;rsquo;t foreseeing which
technologies will dominate, but developing frameworks that lets the world
change, without you drowning in it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleb&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Antifragile&amp;rdquo; celebrates systems that gain from disorder. Mark&amp;rsquo;s 
&amp;ldquo;In Search of Certainty&amp;rdquo; exposes our addiction to false certainties, and 
people who are more than happy to sell them to us. Neither of the books offers
a prophecy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History doesn&amp;rsquo;t move in straight lines. Neither should our thinking. The
surfer doesn&amp;rsquo;t control the ocean. Ha masters responding to it. Fewer damns 
and more surfboards. The waves are coming. The only question is whether 
we&amp;rsquo;ll learn to ride them.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Europe failed Serbia</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/europe-failed-serbia.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/europe-failed-serbia.html</id>
    <published>2025-03-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-09-02T13:30:31+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I remember when Serbia loved Europe. Two decades ago, you could feel the electric
anticipation of EU membership everywhere in the country. As a Hungarian living in
Serbia, I had a unique perspective—watching both my cultural identities navigate
their...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I remember when Serbia loved Europe. Two decades ago, you could feel the electric
anticipation of EU membership everywhere in the country. As a Hungarian living in
Serbia, I had a unique perspective—watching both my cultural identities navigate
their European relationships simultaneously. The values that Europe claimed to
represent weren&amp;rsquo;t new to Hungarians or Serbians. Democratic governance. Rule of law.
Freedom of movement. Independant journalism. They weren&amp;rsquo;t foreign concepts we
needed to adopt. They were principles we had fought for, and in many cases, died for.
My family, friends, and neighbors fought for these values long before the EU membership
was on the table. We weren&amp;rsquo;t becoming European. We were reclaiming what was already
ours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced the EU&amp;rsquo;s failure to protect these values from a dual perspective.
As a Hungarian, I watched Hungary&amp;rsquo;s EU integration while simultaneously seeing Serbia 
kept waiting. I could see how the EU operated differently with different nations. 
The contrast was striking and often disheartening. The EU&amp;rsquo;s treatment of Serbia was
a stark reminder that the EU&amp;rsquo;s values were not universal. They were conditional.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve seen EU representatives lecture Serbia on the importance of a free press while
shaking hands with regime officials who openly dismantled independent media. I&amp;rsquo;ve
witnesed the broken hearts of everyday Serbians watching these performances. The
congitive dissonance between EU&amp;rsquo;s words and actions is a wound that won&amp;rsquo;t heal.
Europe developed a stomach for hypocrisy. They would fly in, make a few speeches,
shake hands with the people who were destroying Serbia, and then fly out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last four months crystallized this hypocrisy perfectly. I stood amond thousands
of fellow citizens, protesting the regime&amp;rsquo;s latest assault on democracy and the
indirect murder of people resulting from years corruption. We took the streets
demanding judicial independence, media freedom, the processing of all the actors
involved in the accident. We weren&amp;rsquo;t asking for special treatment, just the 
foundamental principles Europe claims to champion. This was Europe&amp;rsquo;s moment to 
stand with us, to demonstrate that its commitment to democracy trancends political 
calculations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened instead? I watched European representatives maintan a &amp;ldquo;business as usual&amp;rdquo;
with the regime, giving it legitimacy while we protested outside. These were not
some abstract policies, these were tangible betrayals happening in real time.
Consider what this feels like: marching for values explicitly states in EU founding
documents while watching the EU representatives staying silent. The message cound&amp;rsquo;t
be clearer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Serbian citizens haven&amp;rsquo;t abandoned European values. Europe abandoned us by consistently
choosing a &amp;ldquo;stablecracy&amp;rdquo;. We don&amp;rsquo;t need expressions of &amp;ldquo;deep concern&amp;rdquo;. We need Europe
to align its actions with its words and principles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite everything, I maintain the hope that Europe can transform itself. That it can
rediscover and truly embrace democratic values. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What troubles me most is the change I&amp;rsquo;ve witnessed amound my friends. People who once
spoke of Europe with admiration now speak of it with bitterness. Some actively despise
the EU, something that would have been unthinkable in my social circles just a decade
ago. These aren&amp;rsquo;t people who have rejected democratic values, the rule of law, or 
freedom. They&amp;rsquo;ve rejected the EU&amp;rsquo;s hypocrisy. They&amp;rsquo;ve rejected the EU&amp;rsquo;s betrayal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Europe revealed its priorities. People adjusted accordingly. It&amp;rsquo;s that simple.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Freedom and the Rule of Law</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/freedom-and-the-rule-of-law.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/freedom-and-the-rule-of-law.html</id>
    <published>2025-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-09-02T13:30:31+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rain fell steadily from a gray, oppressive sky as I joined the growing mass of 
people at the city’s edge. Flags and banners waved in the wind, and the sound
of horns filled the air. We were six kilometers from the Republic Square where
the protest...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rain fell steadily from a gray, oppressive sky as I joined the growing mass of 
people at the city&amp;rsquo;s edge. Flags and banners waved in the wind, and the sound
of horns filled the air. We were six kilometers from the Republic Square where
the protest would take place, and the crown was already immense. I had never
seen so many people in one place before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we began our march throught the streets, I found myself sourrounded by a 
cross-section of Serbian society. Professors with rain-spotted glasses walked
alongside farmers who have traveled from all corners of the country. Tech workers
in rainproof jackets shared umbrellas with elderly pensioners who refused to let 
the weather deter them. Mothers pushed strollers, pushing through the crowd with
determination. The atmosphere was electric, and I felt a sense of unity that I had
never experienced before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marked the fourth month of protests since the collapse of at the railway 
station in my hometown where a 300-ton concrete slab had fallen killing 15 people. 
The government had tried to shift the blame to the construction company, 
the original architects, the previous political party, and even some of their 
lower-ranking officials. Every attempt to deflect responsibility had only fueled
the public&amp;rsquo;s anger, and the protests had grown in size and intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students had been the first to take to the streets, demanding justice. They
had been soon joined by workers, farmers, and professionals from all walks of life.
The requests are simple: apply the rule of law, hold those responsible accountable,
and ensure that such a tragedy never happens again. The government&amp;rsquo;s response had
been to ignore the protests, to dismiss them as the work of a foreign conspiracy,
and an attempt to destabilize the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued our march through the city, our numbers swelling with every step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me the most was the sense of unity. I stood shoulder to shoulder with
people I would normally pass on the street without a second glance, some I would
even avaid based on perceived differences. But here, on the streets of Belgrade,
we were all united in our demand for justice. We were all citizens of the same
country, and we all wanted the same thing: freedom and the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we reached the inner city streets, the numbers grew so large that the streets
could no longer contain us. Almost a million people had gathered in the Republic
Square and the sourrounding streets. That is almost 20% of the country&amp;rsquo;s population.
An absolute sea of poeple, civilized and peaceful, yet determined and resolute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protests that erupted across Serbia represent something rare in models political
discourse - a moment when citizens set aside their ideological differences to
defend the system that allows those very differences to exists. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t about
left versus right, young versus old, urban versus rural, or religious versus secular.
It is about preserving the foundamental principles that underpin our society: the
rule of law, accountability, and justice. Or in other words, demanding that the 
government be held to the same standards as the rest of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes these demonstrations particularly significant is their focus not on
immidiate policy outcomes, but on the processes that legitimize the government
itself. The protesters are not demanding a change in the law, but rather the
enforcement of existing laws. They are not calling for a new government, but for
the current one to respect the will of the people. This distiction elevates the
demands from political to profoundly democratic.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The cost of silence</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/questions.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/questions.html</id>
    <published>2025-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-09-02T13:30:31+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently shared a post on X about the asking questions and the importance 
of it in a company culture. Here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temporary discomfort of asking questions is nothing compared to the
permanent cost of not asking them. The biggest red...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently shared a post on X about the asking questions and the importance 
of it in a company culture. Here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temporary discomfort of asking questions is nothing compared to the
permanent cost of not asking them. The biggest red flag in any workplace? When
people stop asking questions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk to be stupid for 5 minutes. Learn. Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me expand on this a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In almost every software project, there&amp;rsquo;s a moment when someone in the room,
often a junior developer or someone from another depertment, has a question but
doesn&amp;rsquo;t ask it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t understand why we&amp;rsquo;re doing this. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is left unasked. The meeting continues. The project moves forward.
The simple question goes unasked because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They don&amp;rsquo;t want to look uninformed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They don&amp;rsquo;t want to slow things down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re afraid of not being a team player, or lack loyalty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re afraid of being wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months, thousands of dollars later, the feature launches with a critical
flaw, or goes by unused. The team is left wondering why they wasted so much time
money. Was it a lack of skill? A lack of resources? A lack of time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. It was a lack of questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a dangerous illusion plaguing most workplaces today. We&amp;rsquo;ve convinced
ourselves that looking smart is more important than getting things right. We
reward confidence over curiosity. We promote people who have answers, any 
answers, rather than those who ask essential questions and actually solve 
problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions are the antibodies that fight organizational disease. They prevent
assumptions from calcifying into &amp;ldquo;truth.&amp;rdquo; They expose weak reasoning before it
becomes costly action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strongest teams don&amp;rsquo;t penalize question - they celebrate them. They 
recognize that &amp;ldquo;stupid questions&amp;rdquo; prevents a truly stupid outcome. The most
valuable skill isn&amp;rsquo;t having all the answers, it&amp;rsquo;s knowing which questions will
unlock progress. Master questioaners cut through complexity and expese the
critical path forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of silence is too high. The cost of not asking questions is too great.
The cost of assuming is your job, your company, and your future.
Dare to ask. Be stupid for 5 minutes. Learn. Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everything Around You Was Someone's Passion Project</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/everything-around-you-was-someones-passion-project.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/everything-around-you-was-someones-passion-project.html</id>
    <published>2025-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-09-02T13:30:31+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look around. Really look. That keyboard you’re typing on, the chair you’re
sitting in, the room you’re in, the building you’re in, the bakery at the end
of your street that sells that amazing bread, your freedom to walk down the
street without fear...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look around. Really look. That keyboard you&amp;rsquo;re typing on, the chair you&amp;rsquo;re
sitting in, the room you&amp;rsquo;re in, the building you&amp;rsquo;re in, the bakery at the end
of your street that sells that amazing bread, your freedom to walk down the
street without fear of being arrested, the ability to read and write, the
ability to communicate with people on the other side of the planet. I can go on
forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re surrounded by other people&amp;rsquo;s devotion and hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not hyporbole. It&amp;rsquo;s fact. Everything you see around you was someone&amp;rsquo;s
passion project. Before the mass production, before the focus groups, before
the value engineering. There was just someone who coudn&amp;rsquo;t let go of an idea.
Someone who looked at the impossible problem and said &amp;ldquo;I can solve this&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s bothering me in Europe right now: We&amp;rsquo;ve become excellent at
pointing out problems. Master critiques. Professional complainers about
everything from government inefficiency to technological stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We write lengthy threads about what&amp;rsquo;s wrong. &lt;br /&gt;
We share detailed analyses of system failures.  &lt;br /&gt;
We craft elegant critiques of institutional problems. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then we wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait for someone else to fix it. Wait for solutions to come from above. Wait
for the system to somehow reform itself. This isn&amp;rsquo;t analysis. It&amp;rsquo;s learned
helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve been conditioned by decades of imperial power structures to think that
change comes from outside. That our role is to merely identify problems, 
complain a lot, and then wait for someone else to fix them. Actual 
implementation is someone else&amp;rsquo;s job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything around us was built by people ignored such compaints. They didn&amp;rsquo;t 
write treatises about why things are broken. They didn&amp;rsquo;t wait for perfect 
conditions. They didn&amp;rsquo;t expect someone else to solve their problems. We didn&amp;rsquo;t
wait for America to innovate for us. We didn&amp;rsquo;t wait for China to manufacture
for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first democracy wasn&amp;rsquo;t built by people waiting for kings to give up power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last three months, my country is the best example of how to break this
cycle. We&amp;rsquo;ve been through a lot in the last couple of decades. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our 
institutions fail us. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our leaders betray us and divide us. We&amp;rsquo;ve 
seen our systems collapse. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our people suffer. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen corruption,
incompetence, and greed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we&amp;rsquo;ve also seen something else. In the last three months, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen students
raise their voices. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen teachers, doctors, and engineers join them. We&amp;rsquo;ve
seen people from all walks of life come together to change things. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen
people who were told to wait for oposition parties to fix things, take matters
into their own hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what Europe needs to learn from this: The right time to start building
was 30 years ago. We fucked it up. The second best time is now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Work can wait, your wedding can't</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/work-can-wait-your-weddig-cant.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/work-can-wait-your-weddig-cant.html</id>
    <published>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-09-02T13:30:31+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I saw something insane on LinkedIn today. A founder bragging about his
co-founder about submitting a pull-request during his own wedding. Let that
sink in for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I saw something insane on LinkedIn today. A founder bragging about his
co-founder about submitting a pull-request during his own wedding. Let that
sink in for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started working in the industry, I thought I knew what hard work was.
Working until my eyes bled out and my fingers were numb. I was wrong. True
hard work isn&amp;rsquo;t about grinding until you drop. It&amp;rsquo;s about passion, focus,
and knowing when to step back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the reality: You can always find another reason to keep working. Just
one more line of code, one more bug to fix. But you can&amp;rsquo;t get back the moments
you miss. You&amp;rsquo;re wedding day is once in a lifetime. No product launch, no
matter how groundbraking will ever compare to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn&amp;rsquo;t just about weddings. It is about the idea that work should consume
every aspect of your life. That you are not commintted unless you are always on.
Always grinding for that carrot that you put infront of yourself. Bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real work - good work - doesn&amp;rsquo;t come from a place of exhaustion. It happens in
focused burst. It happens when you are well-rested, well-fed, and well-loved. The
bug that you are grinding for hours, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably get the right idea when you
are out on walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are things that are actually impressive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shipping great products consistently&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a business that respects people&amp;rsquo;s time and energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enjoying your wedding day with your friends and family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to stop glorifying overwork. If your business can&amp;rsquo;t survive you taking day
off for your wedding, then you don&amp;rsquo;t have a business, you have a ticking time bomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, our legacy won&amp;rsquo;t be the 2k lines of code we wrote on our wedding day.
It will be the relationships we built, the inspiration we gave, and the innovation
we brought to the world. That is the kind of success worth pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work can wait. Your wedding can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
