<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>The path of coding enlightment</title>
  <id>http://shiroyasha.io/</id>
  <link href="http://shiroyasha.io/"/>
  <link href="http://shiroyasha.io/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2025-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Freedom and the Rule of Law</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/freedom-and-the-rule-of-law.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/freedom-and-the-rule-of-law.html</id>
    <published>2025-03-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-03-16T14:29:56+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rain fell steadily from a gray, oppressive sky as I joined the growing mass of 
people at the city’s edge. Flags and banners waved in the wind, and the sound
of horns filled the air. We were six kilometers from the Republic Square where
the protest...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Rain fell steadily from a gray, oppressive sky as I joined the growing mass of 
people at the city&amp;rsquo;s edge. Flags and banners waved in the wind, and the sound
of horns filled the air. We were six kilometers from the Republic Square where
the protest would take place, and the crown was already immense. I had never
seen so many people in one place before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we began our march throught the streets, I found myself sourrounded by a 
cross-section of Serbian society. Professors with rain-spotted glasses walked
alongside farmers who have traveled from all corners of the country. Tech workers
in rainproof jackets shared umbrellas with elderly pensioners who refused to let 
the weather deter them. Mothers pushed strollers, pushing through the crowd with
determination. The atmosphere was electric, and I felt a sense of unity that I had
never experienced before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This marked the fourth month of protests since the collapse of at the railway 
station in my hometown where a 300-ton concrete slab had fallen killing 15 people. 
The government had tried to shift the blame to the construction company, 
the original architects, the previous political party, and even some of their 
lower-ranking officials. Every attempt to deflect responsibility had only fueled
the public&amp;rsquo;s anger, and the protests had grown in size and intensity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The students had been the first to take to the streets, demanding justice. They
had been soon joined by workers, farmers, and professionals from all walks of life.
The requests are simple: apply the rule of law, hold those responsible accountable,
and ensure that such a tragedy never happens again. The government&amp;rsquo;s response had
been to ignore the protests, to dismiss them as the work of a foreign conspiracy,
and an attempt to destabilize the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We continued our march through the city, our numbers swelling with every step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What struck me the most was the sense of unity. I stood shoulder to shoulder with
people I would normally pass on the street without a second glance, some I would
even avaid based on perceived differences. But here, on the streets of Belgrade,
we were all united in our demand for justice. We were all citizens of the same
country, and we all wanted the same thing: freedom and the rule of law.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we reached the inner city streets, the numbers grew so large that the streets
could no longer contain us. Almost a million people had gathered in the Republic
Square and the sourrounding streets. That is almost 20% of the country&amp;rsquo;s population.
An absolute sea of poeple, civilized and peaceful, yet determined and resolute.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The protests that erupted across Serbia represent something rare in models political
discourse - a moment when citizens set aside their ideological differences to
defend the system that allows those very differences to exists. This wasn&amp;rsquo;t about
left versus right, young versus old, urban versus rural, or religious versus secular.
It is about preserving the foundamental principles that underpin our society: the
rule of law, accountability, and justice. Or in other words, demanding that the 
government be held to the same standards as the rest of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What makes these demonstrations particularly significant is their focus not on
immidiate policy outcomes, but on the processes that legitimize the government
itself. The protesters are not demanding a change in the law, but rather the
enforcement of existing laws. They are not calling for a new government, but for
the current one to respect the will of the people. This distiction elevates the
demands from political to profoundly democratic.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The cost of silence</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/questions.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/questions.html</id>
    <published>2025-03-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-03-08T10:50:21+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve recently shared a post on X about the asking questions and the importance 
of it in a company culture. Here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temporary discomfort of asking questions is nothing compared to the
permanent cost of not asking them. The biggest red...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve recently shared a post on X about the asking questions and the importance 
of it in a company culture. Here they are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The temporary discomfort of asking questions is nothing compared to the
permanent cost of not asking them. The biggest red flag in any workplace? When
people stop asking questions. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Risk to be stupid for 5 minutes. Learn. Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me expand on this a bit more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In almost every software project, there&amp;rsquo;s a moment when someone in the room,
often a junior developer or someone from another depertment, has a question but
doesn&amp;rsquo;t ask it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t understand why we&amp;rsquo;re doing this. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question is left unasked. The meeting continues. The project moves forward.
The simple question goes unasked because:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They don&amp;rsquo;t want to look uninformed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They don&amp;rsquo;t want to slow things down.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re afraid of not being a team player, or lack loyalty.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They&amp;rsquo;re afraid of being wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six months, thousands of dollars later, the feature launches with a critical
flaw, or goes by unused. The team is left wondering why they wasted so much time
money. Was it a lack of skill? A lack of resources? A lack of time?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No. It was a lack of questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a dangerous illusion plaguing most workplaces today. We&amp;rsquo;ve convinced
ourselves that looking smart is more important than getting things right. We
reward confidence over curiosity. We promote people who have answers, any 
answers, rather than those who ask essential questions and actually solve 
problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Questions are the antibodies that fight organizational disease. They prevent
assumptions from calcifying into &amp;ldquo;truth.&amp;rdquo; They expose weak reasoning before it
becomes costly action.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strongest teams don&amp;rsquo;t penalize question - they celebrate them. They 
recognize that &amp;ldquo;stupid questions&amp;rdquo; prevents a truly stupid outcome. The most
valuable skill isn&amp;rsquo;t having all the answers, it&amp;rsquo;s knowing which questions will
unlock progress. Master questioaners cut through complexity and expese the
critical path forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cost of silence is too high. The cost of not asking questions is too great.
The cost of assuming is your job, your company, and your future.
Dare to ask. Be stupid for 5 minutes. Learn. Repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Everything Around You Was Someone's Passion Project</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/everything-around-you-was-someones-passion-project.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/everything-around-you-was-someones-passion-project.html</id>
    <published>2025-02-16T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-02-16T14:50:40+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look around. Really look. That keyboard you’re typing on, the chair you’re
sitting in, the room you’re in, the building you’re in, the bakery at the end
of your street that sells that amazing bread, your freedom to walk down the
street without fear...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Look around. Really look. That keyboard you&amp;rsquo;re typing on, the chair you&amp;rsquo;re
sitting in, the room you&amp;rsquo;re in, the building you&amp;rsquo;re in, the bakery at the end
of your street that sells that amazing bread, your freedom to walk down the
street without fear of being arrested, the ability to read and write, the
ability to communicate with people on the other side of the planet. I can go on
forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;re surrounded by other people&amp;rsquo;s devotion and hard work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s not hyporbole. It&amp;rsquo;s fact. Everything you see around you was someone&amp;rsquo;s
passion project. Before the mass production, before the focus groups, before
the value engineering. There was just someone who coudn&amp;rsquo;t let go of an idea.
Someone who looked at the impossible problem and said &amp;ldquo;I can solve this&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And they did.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s bothering me in Europe right now: We&amp;rsquo;ve become excellent at
pointing out problems. Master critiques. Professional complainers about
everything from government inefficiency to technological stagnation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We write lengthy threads about what&amp;rsquo;s wrong. &lt;br /&gt;
We share detailed analyses of system failures.  &lt;br /&gt;
We craft elegant critiques of institutional problems. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And then we wait.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait for someone else to fix it. Wait for solutions to come from above. Wait
for the system to somehow reform itself. This isn&amp;rsquo;t analysis. It&amp;rsquo;s learned
helplessness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve been conditioned by decades of imperial power structures to think that
change comes from outside. That our role is to merely identify problems, 
complain a lot, and then wait for someone else to fix them. Actual 
implementation is someone else&amp;rsquo;s job. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything around us was built by people ignored such compaints. They didn&amp;rsquo;t 
write treatises about why things are broken. They didn&amp;rsquo;t wait for perfect 
conditions. They didn&amp;rsquo;t expect someone else to solve their problems. We didn&amp;rsquo;t
wait for America to innovate for us. We didn&amp;rsquo;t wait for China to manufacture
for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first democracy wasn&amp;rsquo;t built by people waiting for kings to give up power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last three months, my country is the best example of how to break this
cycle. We&amp;rsquo;ve been through a lot in the last couple of decades. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our 
institutions fail us. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our leaders betray us and divide us. We&amp;rsquo;ve 
seen our systems collapse. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen our people suffer. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen corruption,
incompetence, and greed. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But we&amp;rsquo;ve also seen something else. In the last three months, we&amp;rsquo;ve seen students
raise their voices. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen teachers, doctors, and engineers join them. We&amp;rsquo;ve
seen people from all walks of life come together to change things. We&amp;rsquo;ve seen
people who were told to wait for oposition parties to fix things, take matters
into their own hands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what Europe needs to learn from this: The right time to start building
was 30 years ago. We fucked it up. The second best time is now.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Work can wait, your wedding can't</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/work-can-wait-your-weddig-cant.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/work-can-wait-your-weddig-cant.html</id>
    <published>2024-10-08T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2025-02-17T00:21:35+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I saw something insane on LinkedIn today. A founder bragging about his
co-founder about submitting a pull-request during his own wedding. Let that
sink in for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I saw something insane on LinkedIn today. A founder bragging about his
co-founder about submitting a pull-request during his own wedding. Let that
sink in for a moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I started working in the industry, I thought I knew what hard work was.
Working until my eyes bled out and my fingers were numb. I was wrong. True
hard work isn&amp;rsquo;t about grinding until you drop. It&amp;rsquo;s about passion, focus,
and knowing when to step back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the reality: You can always find another reason to keep working. Just
one more line of code, one more bug to fix. But you can&amp;rsquo;t get back the moments
you miss. You&amp;rsquo;re wedding day is once in a lifetime. No product launch, no
matter how groundbraking will ever compare to that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But this isn&amp;rsquo;t just about weddings. It is about the idea that work should consume
every aspect of your life. That you are not commintted unless you are always on.
Always grinding for that carrot that you put infront of yourself. Bullshit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real work - good work - doesn&amp;rsquo;t come from a place of exhaustion. It happens in
focused burst. It happens when you are well-rested, well-fed, and well-loved. The
bug that you are grinding for hours, you&amp;rsquo;ll probably get the right idea when you
are out on walk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are things that are actually impressive:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shipping great products consistently&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Building a business that respects people&amp;rsquo;s time and energy&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enjoying your wedding day with your friends and family&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to stop glorifying overwork. If your business can&amp;rsquo;t survive you taking day
off for your wedding, then you don&amp;rsquo;t have a business, you have a ticking time bomb.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, our legacy won&amp;rsquo;t be the 2k lines of code we wrote on our wedding day.
It will be the relationships we built, the inspiration we gave, and the innovation
we brought to the world. That is the kind of success worth pursuing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work can wait. Your wedding can&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Social Parasites</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/social-parasites.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/social-parasites.html</id>
    <published>2024-10-06T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-10-06T18:32:13+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We’ve recently witnessed a perfect example of this parasitic behavior. A
startup, freshly minted by a once-respected incubator, had the audacity to fork
an open-source project and claim it as their own. They didn’t innovate. They
didn’t improve. They...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;We&amp;rsquo;ve recently witnessed a perfect example of this parasitic behavior. A
startup, freshly minted by a once-respected incubator, had the audacity to fork
an open-source project and claim it as their own. They didn&amp;rsquo;t innovate. They
didn&amp;rsquo;t improve. They simply took.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear: I&amp;rsquo;m not talking about healthy competition or even inspiration
drawn from existing ideas. I&amp;rsquo;m talking about those who shamelessly and completely
take the hard work of others, wrapping it in a shiny new package and calling it
their own.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what happened: This startup PairAI basically took an open-source project 
called Continue, forked it, and are now passing it off as their own groundbreaking
innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And here&amp;rsquo;s the kick-you-in-the-balls: YC&amp;rsquo;s CEO, Garry Tan, defended this copycat
behavior on Twitter. Talk about missing the forest for the trees. Sure, it might
be legal, but that&amp;rsquo;s not the point. The point is that YC is funding startups 
with zero innovation and apparently zero due diligence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being inspired by other projects is one thing. Heck, it&amp;rsquo;s how most of us get
started. I&amp;rsquo;m even fine with copying. But taking someone else&amp;rsquo;s work, changing a 
few lines of code, and calling it your own, and then apply to YC and get funded? 
That&amp;rsquo;s a whole different story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, some might argue that open-source licenses permit such actions. But let me
ask you this: Since when did we start confusing what&amp;rsquo;s legally permissible with
what&amp;rsquo;s ethically right? Since when did &amp;ldquo;not illegal&amp;rdquo; become the bar we&amp;rsquo;re aiming 
for in the tech industry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What message does this send to open-source projects? To the builder and the
maintainers who pour their hearts and souls into open-source projects? It tells
them that their work is up for grabs, ready to be exploited by the first
opportunist who comes along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the thing: Open-source isn&amp;rsquo;t just about the license. It&amp;rsquo;s about the
community. It&amp;rsquo;s about giving back, not just taking. When we use open-source
tools at Operately (and we use them a lot), we always look for ways to contribute
back. Sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s code, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s documentation, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s just
reporting bugs. But we contribute. Because that&amp;rsquo;s how healthy ecosystems work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can we do about it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, if you&amp;rsquo;re an open-source maintainer or contributor, don&amp;rsquo;t let this
discourage you. Keep building, keep sharing. The actions of a few bad actors
don&amp;rsquo;t negate the immense value and importance of what you do. Open-source is
still one of the most powerfull fonces for good, not only in tech, but for the
whole world and society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, to the folks at YC: It&amp;rsquo;s time to step on the brakes. Remember what made
you special in the first place. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t the number of startups you funded. 
It was the quality. The innovation. The community. You are letting it slip
away. For what? A quick flip? A few more unicorns? Is that really worth it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Building a successful project is hard. Building a successful company is even
harder. Really hard. There are no shortcurts. And if there were, they certainly 
wouldn&amp;rsquo;t involve ripping off the hard work of others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So let&amp;rsquo;s call this behavior what it is: parasitic. And let&amp;rsquo;s make sure it has no
place in our industry. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Igor&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Manage Your Time or Someone Else Will Do It for You</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://shiroyasha.io/manage-your-time-or-someone-else-will-do-it-for-you.html"/>
    <id>http://shiroyasha.io/manage-your-time-or-someone-else-will-do-it-for-you.html</id>
    <published>2024-08-25T00:00:00+00:00</published>
    <updated>2024-10-06T18:32:12+00:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Igor Šarčević</name>
    </author>
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the moment we’re born, our time isn’t really our own. Parents, schools,
and later, employers all have a say in how our days unfold. As kids, we’re on
someone else’s schedule. Education systems beat it into us, training us to
march to the drum...&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From the moment we’re born, our time isn’t really our own. Parents, schools,
and later, employers all have a say in how our days unfold. As kids, we’re on
someone else’s schedule. Education systems beat it into us, training us to
march to the drum of a clock that someone else controls. By the time we enter
the workforce, we’re well-prepared to hand over the reins of our time to
another authority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people never break free from this pattern. They move from the structure of
school into the rigid framework of corporate life, where time is often wasted
on pointless tasks. Think about the endless meetings you’ve sat
through—meetings that could have been an email, a quick chat, or even avoided
entirely. It’s astonishing how much time we collectively waste on rituals that
serve no real purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The office itself is a masterclass in time-wasting. Long commutes eat away at
your day. Two hours stuck in traffic might not seem like much, but add that up
over a week, a month, a year. Suddenly, you’ve lost hundreds of hours that
could have been spent on something meaningful. That’s time you could’ve used to
learn a new skill, start a side project, or just have some damn fun. Adventures
don’t just happen—they’re made, and you need time to make them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complete work-life separation isn’t optimal either. When you rigidly divide
work from the rest of your life, you end up competing for time and space with
everyone else. The classic example is the gym at 5 p.m. It’s packed, loud, and
stressful. Go at noon, though, and it’s a different world. You have space, you
have time, and you have freedom. Why not work when you’re most productive, and
live when it’s most enjoyable?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you measure your team’s output by the hours they spend in a chair, you’re
doing it wrong. It’s naive and lazy management. Forcing people to be present
for a fixed number of hours is a waste, plain and simple. It’s not about the
time spent; it’s about what gets done. When you value chair time over actual
work, you’re collectively making everyone’s life worse. You’re stealing time
from them—their most valuable asset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is, if you don’t take control of your time, someone else will. And
they’ll do it in a way that benefits them, not you. Don’t let that happen. Take
the reins, cut out the waste, and reclaim your time. It’s the only way to live
a life that’s truly yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;mdash; Igor&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
